瞧 看这创世以来 拥有更多奇迹的世界
Look, see a world that holds more wonders than any since the Earth was born.
一切作王者 没人名如那从石中拔剑的男孩
And of all who reigned o'er, none had renown like the boy who pulled sword from stone.
但这不是关于那国王 也不是他的歌
But this is not that king...nor is this his song.
让我告诉你一个新的故事
Let me tell you instead a new tale.
我将讲述它 如同我曾听闻
I'll lay it down as I've heard it told.
寄出它的信 追溯它的历史 这是一次勇敢无畏的冒险
Its letters sent, its history pressed, of an adventure brave and bold.
永远地 记于心 铭于石 如同一切伟大的古老神话
Forever set, in heart, in stone, like all great myths of old.
基督诞生了
Christ is born.
基督当然诞生了
Christ is born indeed.
你要去哪
Where are you going?
去教堂
To church!
为什么
Why?
我的靴子 你好啊 艾格尼丝
My boots. Hello, Agnes.
我的靴子在哪
Where are my boots?
你是一名骑士了吗
You a knight yet?
什么
What?
你是骑士了吗
You a knight yet?
- 还不是 - 最好赶紧地
- Not yet. - Better hurry up.
我有的是时间
I've got time.
我有的是很多时间
I've got lots of time.
嘿 埃塞尔
Hey! Essel.
- 嘿 慢点 - 赶紧的
- Hey, slow down. - Hurry up!
埃塞尔
Essel.
我们就待在这吧 来 我们就待在这吧
Let's just stay here. Come on. Let's just stay here.
- 起来 - 不
- Get up. - No.
我还没准备好
I'm not ready yet.
I'm not ready.
圣诞快乐 格林格洛
Merry Christmas, Gryngelot.
你去哪了
Where have you been?
做弥撒
At Mass.
- 你 去做弥撒了 - 是的
- You, at Mass? - Yeah.
一整夜
All night?
是的
Yes.
那好 你的靴子呢
Well, where are your boots?
什么
What?
你的
Where are...
你闻着像是做了弥撒
You do smell like you've been at Mass.
怎么了 你整晚都在喝圣餐吗
What, have you been drinking the sacrament all night?
我爱你 妈妈
I love you, Mother.
你还没着装
You are not dressed.
今年我没有寻欢作乐的心力
I've got no guts for merriment this year.
但这是圣诞日
But it's Christmas.
会有更多圣诞日的 更多盛宴 更多好消息
There'll be more Christmases, more feasts, more glad tidings.
你去吧 找点乐子
You go, make merry.
再告诉我你所见所闻
And tell me what you see.
把小高文带来
Bring young Gawain here.
国王要和你谈谈
The king would speak with you.
你妈妈在哪
Where is thy mother?
她感到不舒服 殿下
She was not feeling herself, my lord.
那就过来 坐这里 挨着我们
Then come. Sit here, besides us.
挨着我和王后
Besides me and my queen.
那不是属于我的位置
That is not my place.
不 今天就随它去吧
No. Let it be, today.
它的主人不在
Its owner is away.
谁知道他什么时候回来呢
Who knows when he will return?
请吧
Please.
很高兴见到你 高文
Good to see you, Gawain.
有家人在身旁真好
Good to have one's family by one's side.
血脉
One's blood.
你的骑士们以你的名义流了足够多的血 他们比我更亲近于你
Surely your knights have spilled enough blood in your name to bind them closer to you than I.
对
True.
但你是我姐姐的孩子 由她的子宫生出
But you are my sister's boy, queefed from her womb.
他们不是
They are not.
今天在这里 我看着我的朋友们 我看到了 所有缪斯都不曾唱或梦见的歌
I look out upon my friends here today and I see... songs...no muse could ever sing or dream of.
但我看向你 却看到了什么
But I turn to thee and I see what?
我认识你 却不了解你
I recognize but I do not know thee.
我说这些不是责备 而是在遗憾 我不曾让你坐在我身边 直到今天 或者在你出生不久 能伏在我膝头
I say this not in reproach, but regret that I have never asked you to sit at my side before this day or upon my knee when thy was newborn.
但今天是圣诞日 我想搭起桥梁
But now it is Christmas, and I wish to build bridges.
所以在我们寻乐子前 你为我准备一份礼物吧
So before we make merry...you make for me a gift.
你告诉我一个关于你的故事 好让我了解你
You tell me a tale of yourself, so that I might know thee.
我没有什么好讲的 殿下
I have none to tell, King.
还没有
Yet.
你还没有什么要讲的
You have none to tell yet.
还没有
Yet.
看看你周围 小高文
Look around you, young Gawain.
你看到了什么
What do you see?
我看到了传说们
I see legends.
不要在他们中间无所事事
Do not take your place amongst them idly.
嗯
Hmm.
那么接着到谁 嗯
So who else then... hmm?
朋友们
Friends...
兄弟 兄弟们和 姐妹们
Brothers... (Brothers...) Brothers and... sisters all. (…sisters all)
我感谢你们在受福之日与我分食面包
I thank thee for breaking bread with me this blessed day.
它是神圣的 因为今早我望向窗外 我看到了由你们双手所塑的土地的形状
And it is blessed... for out my window this morn I looked, and I saw a land shaped...by your hands.
你们以同样的手伸向我们撒克逊的弟兄们 如今在你们的阴影下 他们像婴孩般低头
You have lain those same hands upon our Saxon brethren, who now in your shadow bow their heads like babes.
和平 这由你们为你们的王国带来的和平 所以在这和平里 我此刻告诉你们 我是最幸之人 因为我在你们中间
Peace, peace you have brought to your kingdom, so it is in peace that I... I now say to you... that I... I am the luckiest here today...because I am amongst thee.
我与你们同在
I am amongst thee.
所以在我们庆祝我们的基督诞生前 让我们敬奉他的名行了大事的我们每一个人
So before we celebrate the birth of our Christ, let us honor one of our own who has done great things in His name.
所以说一个故事 或者 或者一场表演
So a tale, or... Or a show perhaps.
你们有什么
What have thee?
谁能用关于你们自己的神话或篇章来取悦我和王后
Who can regale me and my queen with some myth or canto of thine own purport?
等等
Hold.
噢 最伟大的国王 让我沉浸在这友好的圣诞游戏中吧
Oh, Greatest Of Kings, indulge me in this friendly Christmas game.
让你的骑士中 最勇猛最不羁的人站出来 拿起武器 试着光荣地给我一击
Let whichever of your knights is boldest of blood and wildest of heart step forth, take up arms, and try with honor to land a blow against me.
无论谁伤了我 都将拥有这个 我的武器
Whomsoever nicks me shall lay claim to this, my arm.
它的荣耀和财富将属于你
It's glory and riches shall be thine.
但是
But...
你的冠军必须遵守这点:
thy champ must bind himself to this:
要是他给了一击 那么一年后的圣诞 他必须到那边去找我 往北行6日 到绿教堂
Should he land a blow, then one year and Yuletide hence, he must seek me out yonder, to the Green Chapel six nights to the North.
他会在那发现我 他要屈膝 让我回敬他一击
He shall find me there and bend the knee and let me strike him in return.
无论是脸颊上的划痕 还是喉咙上的割伤 我都将以牙还牙 然后凭信任和友谊 我们就此别过
Be it a scratch on the cheek or a cut on the throat, I will return what was given to me, and then in trust and friendship we shall part.
那么 谁愿同我打赌呢
Who, then, who is willing to engage with me?
醒醒 女王
Help. Queen.
这是你自己的挑战吗
This challenge is thine own?
虽然我的意志渴望跃过这张桌子去面对你 但我的身体却无法跟随
Though my will longs to leap across this table and meet thee, my body will not follow.
我们中一定有人愿意面对这位骑士 按照他的条件
Surely there is one amongst us here who will meet this knight on his terms.
我会的
I will do it.
我会面对他
I will meet him.
我将面对你
I will meet thee.
你明白这个挑战吗
You understand this challenge?
我明白
I do.
我想我明白
I think I do.
记住 这只是一场游戏
Remember, it is only a game.
我需要一把剑
I need a sword.
我需要 我需要一把剑
I need... I need a sword.
高文
Gawain.
来吧 绿骑士
Have at me, Green Knight.
行动吧 不然我要行动了
Make a move or I shall make mine.
这是什么
What is this?
一个诡计
A trick?
站起来 面对我
Stand up and face me!
你期待我怎么做
What do you expect me to do?
拿出勇气
Have courage.
很好
Very well.
你搁下了挑战
You laid down your challenge.
我接受了 现在也接受
I accepted it and I accept it still.
永远别忘记这个圣诞日 在这里发生的一切
Never forget what happened here upon this Christmas Day!
一年后
One year hence...
那是什么感觉
What did it feel like?
那是什么感觉 当你
What did it feel like when you...
就像把瓜切半
Like cutting a melon in two.
那么那是什么感觉
And what does that feel like?
没什么感觉
Like nothing.
你害怕了吗
Were you afraid?
不
No.
那么你就是说说吗
Are you just saying that?
我还在在这里 而他不在
I am here, and he is not.
国王把他的剑借给我了 你知道吗
The king lent me his sword, did you know that?
你握着它
You held it?
是的 我不只握着它
Well, I did more than hold it.
看啊 勇敢的高文阁下 斩首如切瓜 谁也不能 得到它了
Behold, Brave Sir Gawain, chopper of heads...severer of melons, who cannot...get it up.
你是高文 是吗
You're Gawain, aren't you?
不 你肯定搞错了
Nah, you must be mistaken.
不 不 你就是他
No, no, you're him.
你总在这里 几乎都在
You're always here. Always about.
大多数晚上几乎没站稳离开过
Scarcely leave upright most nights.
又不是在圣诞日
But not on Christmas.
你听说过吗
Have you heard?
这个男孩杀了绿骑士
This boy slew the Green Knight.
用他自己的斧头 他砍下巨人的头 而现在他和我们一起喝酒
With his own axe, he lopped off the giant's head, and now he drinks with us!
但他妈妈是个女巫
But his mother's a witch.
起身
Rise.
坐下
Sit.
我一直在等你
I've been waiting for you.
你没听见我的呼唤吗
Did you not hear me calling?
我的牙疼
My tooth hurts.
又一年已快过去了
Another year nearly gone already.
你想过圣诞日到来前 你要做什么吗
Have you thought what you will do when Christmas comes?
那不就是一场游戏吗
Was it not just a game?
也许是
Perhaps.
但它还没有圆满
But it is not complete.
你真的相信他会坐教堂里 数着日子 消磨一年等着我的到来吗
You truly believe he's sitting in a chapel, counting the hours, whiling away the year waiting for me to come?
好吧 我不知道
Well, I do not know.
你要告诉我
You will tell me.
你必须找到他
You must seek him out.
但如果死亡在等我呢
And if death awaits me?
噢 我确实不知道会有谁在时辰到前 前去迎接死亡
Oh, I do not know of any man who has not marched up to greet death before his time.
你为什么要为我指明道路
Why are you holding me to this light?
对你而言 想要伟大是错的吗
Is it wrong to want greatness for you?
我怕我生来就不是伟大之人
I fear I am not meant for greatness.
嗯
Mm.
在你脸上有泥土
You have mud on your face.
愿圣母保佑你的五指强健 五官敏锐
May the Blessed Virgin keep your five fingers strong, your five senses sharp.
愿她的五种快乐激励你
May her five joys inspire you.
其子的五个伤口予你热情
The five wounds of her son give you fervor.
骑士的五种美德会照亮你的道路
And the five virtues of a knight light your way.
遵守你的约定吧 小高文
Keep thy covenant, young Gawain.
如果上帝朝你微笑
And if God smiles on thee,
那是盼你归来
then hurry thee back.
我们身旁的座位等候你
Thy seat besides us waits.
你真的要去吗
Are you really going to go?
我应该吗
Should I?
我更喜欢你现在的脑袋
I like your head better where it is.
我承诺了 我立下了约定
I gave my word. I made a covenant.
这就是愚蠢的人之所以丧命
This is how silly men perish.
或者勇敢的人之所以变得伟大
Or how brave men become great.
为什么要伟大
Why greatness?
为什么善良还不足够
Why is goodness not enough?
现在拿上这个
Take this now.
离开时把它系在腰间
Wear it about your waist as you go.
- 如果你回来时还戴着它 - 我能回来吗
- And if you wear it still when you return... - Will I return?
你回来时 你一定要昂首阔步
When you return, you will come with your head held high.
我保证 你不会受到伤害
I promise, you will not come to harm.
还有 孩子
And, boy...
我的孩子 不要浪费这机会
My boy... do not waste this.
高文 高文
Gawain! Gawain!
我得到了一把剑
I've got a sword!
加文 伟大之流
Gawain! Great tide.
祝你好运
Good luck!
祝你好运 高文
Good luck, Gawain!
你还喜欢我吗
Do you still fancy me?
我让你快乐吗
Do I make you happy?
是的
Yes.
即使我在这 你在那
Even though I'm here and you're there?
是的
Yes.
如果我请求你让我做你的夫人 你会怎么说
What will you say if I asked you to make me your lady?
- 一位夫人 - 你的夫人
- A lady? - Your lady.
我可以给你比任何夫人都多的金子
I could give you more gold than any lady has.
我已经有你的金子了
I already have your gold.
如果我想坐在你身边 握住你的手 还有 听你的声音呢
What if I wanted to sit by your side and... take your hand and... have your ear?
你会怎么说
What will you say to that?
为什么 当然 埃塞尔
"Why, yes, Essel.
我非常乐意
"I'd like that very much.
我的耳朵 我的手 我的心都归你了
"You may have my ear and my hand and heart.
我会是国王 而你是王后
"And I will be king and you my queen.
你会是我的夫人
"You'll be my lady...
我会是你的男人
"and I'll be your man."
你是谁
Who are you?
只是个旅行者 朋友
Just a traveler, friend.
你看起来像名骑士
You look like a knight.
我只是经过
Just passing through.
啊 我猜你想要分享一些东西 对吧
Ah. I take it you'll want some of the shares, so, huh?
一些什么
Of what?
所有的这些
All of this!
为什么他们没有被埋葬
Why weren't they buried?
都死了 都死了
All dead. All dead.
没人埋葬他们
No one to bury 'em.
不过你知道 大自然会有办法的
Though you know, nature will do its trick.
她会吸它们 然后塞紧
She'll suck 'em in and tuck 'em tight.
诶 话这么说 我有两个兄弟在这以外的什么地方
Eh, in saying that, I do have two brothers out here somewhere.
他们出走了 他们再没回家
And they marched off. They never came home.
你要直到 如果不是因为我妈 我早就来这了 我早就来这了
You know, if it weren't for my ma, I would've been here. I would've been here!
我也会在这里
I would've been here too!
他们都在这里了
They all came here!
虽然我会撑得久一点
Though I'd have lasted longer.
那国王 他们说那个国王 他独自就杀了960人
The king, they say... They say the king, he killed 960 all on his lonesome.
- 900 吗 - 对啊
- Nine hundred, eh? - Uh-huh.
不过 换成是我 我将会站足够久 开我的弓
Now, if it was me, I'da stayed upright long enough to take my shot.
你的斧子真不错
That's a nice axe you got.
你用那斧子战斗过吗
You do some fighting with that axe?
- 有时候吧 - 在这里吗
- Here and there. - Here?
只在别处
Only there.
在这里 我就是经过
Here, I'm just passing through.
去哪
To where?
我去北方
I go North.
北方 噢
North, oh!
北方是一个方向 很好
North is a direction, all right.
就是北方吗
Just North?
去绿教堂
To the Green Chapel.
噢
Oh!
你知道它吗
Do you know of it?
绿教堂 嗯
The Green Chapel, eh?
那边有条小溪
There's a stream yonder.
它向北湖流去
It runs Northlike.
我是说 如果我 如果我的方位的话
I mean, if I've... If I've got my bearing.
对的 对的 它向北湖流去
Yeah, yeah, it runs Northlike.
但如果你跟着它走一天半 你就会到达一个小教堂
But if you follow that for a day and a half, you'll come to a chapel.
至少我觉得那是个小教堂
At least I think it's a chapel.
它是 嗯 它是 嗯 它总体上不算绿色 但我的意思是 它绝对是带绿色的 有苔藓和 嗯 腐坏物和废墟 但也许就是你在找的
It's, uh... It's, uh, yeah, it's... It's not green on the whole, but I mean, it's definitely greenish, with the moss and the, uh... the rot and ruins, but perhaps it's what you seek.
小溪在那边吗
The stream is yonder?
嗯
Mmm-hmm.
是这条路
It's this way.
穿过田野 与森林交汇之处
Past the field, where the forest meets.
我会找到它 谢谢你
I will seek it out. My thanks to you.
谢谢你
My thanks to you.
走吧
Come on.
我的指向对你一文不值吗
Are my directions not worth anything to you?
谢谢了
My thanks.
我说 我的指向对你一文不值吗
I said, are my directions not worth anything to you?
我是说 像你这样的骑士能够为我这样的可怜虫留下一小点的善举吗
I mean, a knight like you could spare a wretch like me just a small, small act of kindness.
在这 一个善举
Here. A kindness.
噢
Oh!
等等
Wait.
北湖 看到了吗
Northlike. See?
谢谢你
Thank you.
留意溪流
Remember the stream.
我会的
I will.
因为它很狡猾
'Cause it gets tricky.
给你的 孩子
Here you go, boy.
真是个好孩子
That's a good boy.
好孩子
Good boy.
来吧 我们走
Come on. Let's go.
你好啊
Hello, there.
你好
Hello.
看好 看好
Now, now.
- 拜托 - 是吗 拜托
- Please. - Yeah, please?
- 拜托 拜托 - 拜托
- Please. Please. Please! - Please!
- 拜托 - 拜托
- Please. - Please!
拜托 拜托
Please! Please! Please! Please!
拜托
Please.
噢
Oh.
还不够 只是还不够
'Tweren't enough. Just 'tweren't enough.
嘿 嘿 你要去哪
Hey, hey, hey! Where you off to, huh?
你要去哪里 骑士的使命吗
Where you off to? A knightly quest?
我不是名骑士
I'm not a knight.
但你说你是
But you said you were.
我从没说过 是你说的
I never said that. You said that.
我从没说过我是骑士
I never said I was a knight.
- 你是吗 - 不 不 我不是
- But are you? - No! No, I'm not.
噢 嗯
Oh. Hmm.
- 好吧 你看着像 - 对啊
- Well, you look like one. - Aye.
闻着像名骑士
Smells like a knight.
- 噢 - 拜托
- Oh... - Please...
噢 噢
Oh. Oh!
啊
Ah.
哇哦
Whoa!
Whoo!
耶
Yeah!
那就告诉我吧 那边真有小教堂吗
Just tell me, then. Is there really a chapel?
你就在它里面
You're in it.
哇哦 看这
Whoa! Watch it.
让我拿拿它
Let me hold that.
它适合我
It suits me.
这适合我 对吧
This suits me, huh?
你要好好休息 我勇敢的小骑士
You rest your bones, my brave little knight.
我会完成你的使命
I'll finish your quest for you.
我会好好吃完的
I'll finish it good.
嘿 你要去哪
Hey! Where are you going?
- 嘿 - 嘿呀
- Hey! - Hyah!
格林格洛
Gryngelot!
有人吗
Hello.
你在我床上干什么
What are you doing in my bed?
我很抱歉 我 我没有看见你
I'm very sorry. I... I did not see you.
我以为附近没人
I thought there was no one about.
我不是有意冒犯你
I did not mean to offend thee.
等等
Wait.
是我父亲让你来的吗
Did my father send for you?
不 他没有
No. He did not.
我不认识你父亲
I do not know your father.
我只是一个迷路的旅人 在寻找过夜之处 不过我马上会离开
I am just a lost traveler, seeking rest for the night, but I will leave forthwith.
你要去哪
Where are you going?
家
Home.
我回家
I'm headed home.
你迷失了道路吗
And you've lost your way?
是的
Yes.
我也迷失了什么东西
I've lost something as well.
你能帮我找到它吗
Will you help me find it?
你在干什么
What are you doing?
- 我只是 - 别碰我
- I was just... - Do not touch me.
一名骑士应该更清楚
A knight should know better.
你叫什么名字 女士
What is your name, my lady?
我叫温尼弗雷德
I'm called Winifred.
你听说过我吗
You heard of me?
没有
No.
那里
There.
我需要找什么
What is it I'm looking for?
我的头
My head.
你的头在你的脖子上 女士
Your head is on your neck, my lady.
不 它没有
No. It is not.
可能看着像是 但并非如此
It might look like it is, but it is not.
它在泉水处
It is in the spring.
那它是怎么到那的
Well, how did it happen to get there?
一位爵士来寻求庇护 就像你一样
A lord came seeking shelter, like thee.
也许他就是你
Perhaps he was thee.
- 是吗 - 不是
- Was he? - No.
你确定吗
You certain?
是的
Yes.
这位领主想和我睡一起
This lord sought to lay with me.
我击退了他 但他夜晚回来 砸坏了我的门
I fought him off, but he returned in the night and broke down my door.
我想逃跑 但他砍下了我的头
I tried to flee, but he cut off my head.
他把它扔进了泉里 而现在 无论我怎么努力 我都拿不到它
He threw it in the spring, and now, try as I might, I cannot get at it.
女士
My lady...
My lady.
你是真实存在的 还是一个幽灵
Are you real, or are you a spirit?
这有什么区别
What is the difference?
我只是需要我的头
I just need my head.
今年过去之前 我也需要
As will I before the year is out.
如果我进去找到了它 你会给我什么作为回报
If I go in there and find it, what would you offer me in exchange?
为什么你问我这个
Why would you ask me that?
究竟为什么你问我这个
Why would you ever ask me that?
高文
Gawain...
女士
My lady.
现在我能看见你了
Now I can see thee.
我会以我对你的一切关爱将你击倒
And I will strike thee down with every care I have for thee.
绿骑士是你所认识的人
The Green Knight is someone you know.
好吧 如果你想就进来吧
Well, come on in if you want.
嘿 嘿
Hey! Hey!
你要往哪个方向去
Which direction are you headed?
一个疲惫的旅人能站到你的肩膀上穿过山谷吗
Might a weary traverse the valley on your shoulder?
朋友
Friend!
欢迎光临
Welcome!
放松 放轻松
Easy now, easy.
- 你是谁 - 别害怕
- Who are you? - Have no fear.
- 你和朋友们在一块 - 我的衣服呢
- You're among friends. - Where are my clothes?
嘘 放轻松
Shh. Easy.
现 现在是哪天
Wha... What day is it?
是12月21日
It is December the 21st.
噢 别担心 高文爵士
Oh, fear not, Sir Gawain.
你只是睡了一晚
You've only slept through the night.
你怎么知道我的名字
How do you know my name?
我知道的不仅是你的名字
I know more than just your name.
你必须吃东西
You must eat.
新年之际 我要去西部旅行
See, upon the new year, I travel to the West.
一周后 空屋归你
Came you one week hence and an empty home greet you.
不过在那之前 我会去打猎
Till then, though, I will hunt.
我打猎 你休息 这样对我俩都好
I will hunt, you shall rest and we shall both be all the better for it.
啊
Ah.
这位就是我们的朋友 夫人 刚从睡梦中苏醒
And here is our friend, my lady, fresh from his slumbers.
还有这里 朋友 这是你补充体力的早餐
And here, friend, is your breakfast to replenish your strength.
想必 你会需要它
Surely, you will need it.
这是为什么
Why is that?
因为你的英勇 高文爵士 前来面对绿骑士
Because you are brave, Sir Gawain, come to face the Green Knight.
我敢说这片土地上的每张桌子都听说过你 唱过你的歌
I dare say every table in this land has heard of you and sung your song.
高文爵士 最好最高尚的骑士 穿过荒野 寻找他的命运
Sir Gawain, the finest and most virtuous knight, seeking his destiny across these lands.
也许我不是你想象的那样
Perhaps you think that I am something I'm not.
想象的哪样
Such as what?
你打算在这住多久
How long will you stay with us?
我必须在圣诞前履约
I must make my appointment by Christmas.
我会吃完这些 表示感谢 然后离开
I will eat and give thanks and then take my leave.
荒谬 你难道不知道
Nonsense. Don't you know?
绿教堂就在不远
The Green Chapel is not far.
你知道它吗
Do you know of it?
你非常接近那里了
You are very nearly there.
就在河的下游 不到一天的路程
It's down the river, not one day's journey.
你确定那么近吗
Are you certain it is that close?
你抵达终点了 高文
You are at the end of your quest, Gawain.
也许比你预期的早一些
A little sooner than you expected, perhaps.
但目前情况就是如此
But such is the case for us all.
下面是将发生的事情
Here is what will happen.
在圣诞日清晨 我们会送你上路
On Christmas morn, we will send you on your way.
夜幕降临时 你就会站在你命运的入口
And by nightfall, you will be at the doorway of your destiny.
所以就多待一会儿 休息吧
So stay a while. Rest.
享受一下
And make yourself content.
你发现了什么
What did you find?
我从不知道世上有这么多书
I never knew so many books even existed.
你都读过吗
Have you... Have you read them all?
是的
Yes.
我都读过
All of them I've read.
一些由我著述 一些由我抄写
Some I've written, some I've copied.
它们是我所闻之事 是所听之歌
They're tales I've heard, songs that have been sung to me.
我写下它们 而有时 我并不告诉任何人
I write them down and sometimes... Don't tell anyone this.
有时 当我看到改进余地时 我就完成它们
Sometimes when I see room for improvements...I make them.
- 你喜欢书吗 - 是的
- Do you like books? - Yes.
那好 为什么不为你不拿上一本
Well... Why don't you take one with you?
我不能
I couldn't.
噢 但是快到圣诞日了
Oh, but it is nearly Christmas.
这里
Here.
这是给你的
This one's for you.
谢谢你
I thank you.
骑士不该给女士一个吻以示感谢吗
Should not a knight offer a lady a kiss in thanks?
你愿意为我坐着吗
Will you sit for me?
为你坐着
Sit for you?
为一幅肖像
For a portrait.
啊 我已经制作了我的肖像
Ah. I've had my portrait made already.
但不是由我
Not by me.
爱是刺进我心 痛苦的矛
"Ant love is to myn herte gon" "With one spere so kene..."
保持不动
Hold very still.
日夜间我的血干涸 我的心凋亡卷曲
"Nyht ant day my blod hit drynkes" "Myn herte deth me tene."
那是幅很奇怪的画
That's a very queer painting.
那是什么
What's that?
什么
What?
这个
This.
这是一个表示
It's a token.
表示什么 表示祝你好运吗
For what? For good luck?
表示爱
For love?
不是
No.
骑士当然懂得爱
Surely a knight knows something of love.
我不懂
I don't.
真的吗
Truly?
高文
Gawain!
看看我为你带来了什么
Look what I have brought you!
当我驱赶他时 我在想这是多好的礼物啊
When I dispersed of him, I thought what a gift!
给我新朋友的礼物
What a gift for my new friend.
我该拿它怎么办
What shall I do with it?
那 在你的旅途中带上它吧
Well, take it with you for your journey.
你想你说过它在不远处
I thought you said it was not far.
我的意思是之后 你回家的旅途
I mean your journey home, after.
让我们彼此许下承诺
Let us make a promise to each other.
我明天和后天会去打猎
I hunt tomorrow and the day after.
无论森林给我什么 我都会为你带回最好的
Whatever the forest offers me, I will bring you home the best.
而你要回赠我 任何你在这里可能得到的
And you give me in turn whatever you might receive here.
我在这里能得到 有什么不是你的
What might I receive here that is not already yours?
谁知道呢
Who knows?
这屋里满是奇怪的东西
This house is full of strange things.
但话说回来 我在到处都见到不合逻辑的事
But then again, I see things everywhere that bear no logic.
你见过一只鹰杀一匹马吗
Have you ever seen a hawk kill a horse?
就俯冲下来然后 呼 太可怕了
Just swoop down and... Phew. It's terrible.
每个人至少应看一次
Every man should see it at least once.
但世界就是这样
But that is the world.
这个世界容纳了各种各样的奥秘
And the world is fit for all manner of mysteries.
不过 男人的屋子 对所有这些来讲 应该是安全的
A man's home, though, should be safe from all that.
墙挨着墙 齐平 垂直
One wall joined with another, line and plumb.
非常好 坚固的墙壁
Good, strong walls,
还有内部的火源
and a fire within.
为什么他是绿的 你认为呢
Why is he green, do you think?
那个骑士吗
The knight?
是的
Yes.
他生来就这样吗
Was he born that way?
也许这是他脸红时血的颜色
Perhaps it is the color of his blood when he blushes.
但为什么是绿的
But why green?
为什么不是蓝色或红色
Why not blue or red?
因为他不是世间之物
Because he is not of this earth.
但绿色是大地的颜色 生物的颜色 生命的颜色
But green is the color of earth, of living things, of life.
- 还有腐坏 - 是的
- And of rot. - Yes.
是的
Yes.
我们用它装饰我们的大厅 给我们的亚麻布染色
We deck our halls with it and dye our linens.
但如果它爬上了石铺路 我们会把它擦洗干净 尽快地
But should it come creeping up the cobbles, we scrub it out, fast as we can.
当它在我们的皮肤下开花 我们会将它榨干
When it blooms beneath our skin, we bleed it out.
而当我们 一同 发现我们触及的超出了我们能掌控的 我们就将它砍下 将它踏灭 我们在它顶上传播我们自己 把它扼杀在我们的腹下 但它又回来了
And when we, together all, find that our reach has exceeded our grasp, we cut it down, we stamp it out, we spread ourselves atop it and smother it beneath our bellies, but it comes back.
它不拖拉 也不等策划或阴谋
It does not dally, nor does it wait to plot or conspire.
某天将它连根拔起 隔天 它就在那 隐约出现
Pull it out by the roots one day and then next, there it is, creeping in around the edges.
当我们寻找红色时 绿色来了
Whilst we're off looking for red, in comes green.
红是欲望的颜色 而绿是欲望遗留之物 在心里 在子宫里
Red is the color of lust, but green is what lust leaves behind, in heart, in womb.
绿色是当热忱衰退 激情停息 也是当我们死去时 留下的东西
Green is what is left when ardor fades, when passion dies, when we die, too.
你离去时 你的脚印将长满青草
When you go, your footprints will fill with grass.
苔藓将覆盖你的墓碑 当太阳升起 绿色将覆着一切 在它的浓荫中
Moss shall cover your tombstone, and as the sun rises, green shall spread over all, in all its shades and hues.
铜绿将追上你的剑 你的钱币 你的城垛而 尽你所能吧 你珍视的一切都将臣服于它
This verdigris will overtake your swords and your coins and your battlements and, try as you might, all you hold dear will succumb to it.
你的皮肤 你的骨头
Your skin, your bones.
你的美德
Your virtue.
那么你希望收获什么 当面对所有的这 这颜色
And what do you hope to gain from facing all of this... this hue?
荣誉吗
Honor?
你是在问我吗
Are you asking me?
- 没有 - 嗯
- No. - Hmm.
荣誉
Honor.
这就是为什么骑士做他应做的事
That is why a knight does what he does.
这就是你人生中最想要的吗
And this is what you want most in life?
成为一名骑士
To be a knight.
不是 荣誉
No, honor.
你不善于答问
You are not very good with questions.
这是我想要的人生的一部分
It is part of the life I want.
而这 就是这部分所需要的全部吗
And this is all it takes for that part to be had?
你只做了一件事 你回家后就变了一个人 一个可敬的人 就像这样吗
You'll do this one thing, you return home a changed man, an honorable man? Just like that?
是的
Yes.
嗯
Hmm.
噢 我希望能看到全新的你
Oh, I wish I could see the new you.
但也许我们会想念我们的老朋友 我们的乐趣 我们的游戏
But perhaps we will miss our old friend and our fun and our games.
- 夫人 - 嘘
- My lady... - Shh.
昨天你为什么不来我的房间
Why did you not come to my chambers yesterday?
我不能
I couldn't.
你不能吗
You couldn't?
不是 但
No, but...
但你想
But you wanted to.
是的
Yes.
现在呢
And now?
- 我想我能 但是 - 但是 - 这是不对的
- I would that I could, but... - But... - It isn't right.
嗯
Hmm.
是不对的
Isn't right.
是不对
No.
你相信魔法吗
Do you believe in magic?
什么
What?
巫术 你相信吗
In witchcraft. Do you believe in it?
是的 我相信
Yes. I do.
它就在我们身边
It is all around us.
我有个礼物给你
I have a gift for you.
你从哪得到的
Where did you get that?
我制作了它
I made it.
它的织线里缝着一种法术
There's an enchantment sewn into its threads.
穿上它 你将永远不被击倒
Wear it and you will never be struck down.
通过什么
By what?
通过人 或者神灵 或任何其他工具
By man, or spirit, or any other implements.
我保证 只要它在你腰间 你就不会受到伤害
I promise, you will not come to harm...as long as it is about your waist.
你是认真的吗
Do you mean it?
是的
Yes.
你想要它吗 哼
You want it? Huh.
你想要它吗
Do you want it?
是的
Yes.
那告诉我
Then tell me.
没事的 告诉我
It's okay, tell me.
我想要它
I want it.
很好
Good.
那就拿去吧
Then take it.
来吧 拿走吧 拿去吧
Go on, take it. Take it.
你不是骑士
You are no knight.
高文
Gawain!
你要去哪
Where are you going?
我必须履我的约
I must make my appointment.
噢 毕竟是你的事
Oh, on your own, after all?
我们的游戏怎么办
What of our game?
我不想要你的游戏 你的礼物 你的好意
I don't want your games, or your gifts, or your kindness.
你确定你没有什么想给我的吗
Are you certain there is nothing you wish to give me?
有些东西
There is something.
我想我可以从你这里拿走
And I think I can take it from you.
放开我 我们各走自己的路吧
Unhand me and let us go our ways.
很好
Very well.
高文
Gawain!
我 我今早在一处陷阱抓住了这个可怜的伙计
I... I caught this poor fellow in a trap this morning.
我本打算把他给你 但我认为我们应当把他留给大自然吧
I was going to give him to you, but I suppose we should leave him to nature.
再见了 高文爵士
Farewell, Sir Gawain.
还有圣诞快乐
And happy Christmas!
如果你再经这条路回来 我们应该已经离开了
If you come back by this way again, we shall be gone!
为什么你要阻止我
Why do you stop me?
我不能逗留
I cannot tarry.
走那条路 你的末日就在跟前
Go that way and your doom is at hand.
你会不得怜悯 不得善终
You will find no mercy. No happy end.
这是什么巫术
What witchcraft is this?
不是巫术
No witchcraft.
你找那人跟我一样野蛮 但不懂分寸
He you seek is as wild as I, but knows no measure.
我知道我面对的是什么
I know what I face.
如果有人真的知道 他就会高兴地忍受他的屈辱 昂首挺胸地转身离开 如他所愿地结束他的歌
If any man truly knew, he would bear his shame happily and turn away, head held high, to end his song as he saw fit.
他的秘密将由我保守
His secret would be safe with me.
你是这个人吗
Are you this man?
不
No.
你腰间的咒语可不这么说
The spell about your waist says otherwise.
这只是一块脏抹布
This is just a dirty rag.
那就把它留在这
Leave it here, then.
这是一份礼物
It was a gift.
你要去的地方不需要礼物
No need for gifts where you are headed.
来吧 回家去
Come, come home.
跟我回家吧
Come home with me.
反正我从没要求你的陪伴
I never asked for your company anyway!
你来了
You came.
好家伙 到圣诞日了吗
Good sir, is it Christmas?
是的
Yes.
你记得你砍了我哪里吗
Do you recall where you cut me?
我记得
I do.
那你是否清楚回击的这下吗
And have you come to see that blow returned?
我清楚
I have.
那就跪下 我们来完成我们的游戏
Then kneel, and we shall complete our game.
现在吗
Now?
是
Aye.
现在 一击即中如同你给的
Now, one strike as good as you gave.
阁下 你退缩了
Sir, you flinch.
我知道
I know.
当我们位置颠倒 我有显露害怕吗
Did I show signs of fear when our positions were reversed?
我不如你那般自信
I'm not so confident as thee.
你有一年的时间寻找勇气
You have had a year to find courage.
一年或者一百年 都不会有什么区别
One year or a hundred, it wouldn't make a difference.
给我一点时间
Give me a moment.
你准备好了吗
Are you ready?
是的
Yes.
那么我将劈下
Then I shall get to hacking.
等等 等等
Wait! Wait.
这是 真的只是这样吗
Is this... really all there is?
那些 这些都
Is that... Is this...
还应该有什么
What else ought there be?
不 不 我很抱歉
No! No. I'm sorry.
我不能 我很抱歉
I cannot. I'm sorry.
盛开的可人的百合花 棕色的鸟儿唱着自己的旋律 盛开的可人的百合花 我去见圣玛丽
♪ Bloom, bloom Sweet lily flower. The brown bird Sings its melody. Bloom, bloom Sweet lily flower. I go to see Saint Mary. ♪
握紧 用你的手握紧我的手 握紧我的手
♪ Hold, hold my hand in yours. Hold, hold my hand. ♪
冷夜渐长 再无分文支付我路途
♪ Cold, cold the night Has grown. No coin to pay the fare. ♪
嘘
Shh.
握紧 亲密的爱人请握紧我的手 握紧我的手
♪ Hold, hold my hand Dear love. Hold, hold my hand. ♪
冷夜渐长 再无分文缓解我渴求
♪ Cold, cold the night Has grown. No coin to ease my want. ♪
盛开的可人的百合花 棕色的鸟儿颤栗地唱着它的旋律
♪ Bloom, bloom Sweet lily flower. The brown bird Trills its melody. ♪
盛开的可人的百合花 我去见圣玛丽
♪ Bloom, bloom Sweet lily flower. I go to see Saint Mary. ♪
唱你自己的歌吧 欧嘞 欧嘞 欧嘞
♪ Sing thy song, ole, ole, ole. ♪
如今这孩子他来了
♪ Now the child he come. ♪
躺在欢乐和恶劣中
♪ Ye lie in joy and wickedness. ♪
唱你自己的歌吧 欧嘞 欧嘞 唱你自己的歌吧 欧嘞 欧嘞
♪ Sing thy song, ole, ole, ole. Sing thy song Ole, ole, ole. ♪
等等
Wait.
好了 现在我准备好了
There. Now I'm ready.
现在我准备好了
I'm ready now.
干得好 我勇敢的骑士
Well done, my brave knight.
现在
Now...
砍下你的头
Off with your head.
快乐起来 亲爱的主 在这圣诞之日 荆棘随我飞翔 快乐起来 亲爱的主 赐我你的礼物 我发誓我现在自由了 带着迅速的红宝石
♪ Be merry, sweet Lord. On this yules day. A briar come with me and fly. Be merry, sweet Lord. On giving me thine gift. I swear that I'm free now. With rubies so swift. ♪
快乐起来 亲爱的主 请原谅我 快乐与财富 柔和的旋律 快乐起来 亲爱的主 一千次感谢上帝 盛情享用 现在就去吧 兴奋起来吧
♪ Be merry, sweet Lord. And beg pardon me. Pleasure and treasure And soft melody. Be merry, sweet Lord. Thank God thousand time. Feast up and go now. And be the sweet cream. ♪
快乐起来 亲爱的主 我甜蜜的苦求的光
♪ Be merry, sweet Lord. Me sweet achen licht. ♪
快乐起来 亲爱的主 在这圣诞之日
♪ Be merry, sweet Lord. On this yules day. ♪